-==www.RagBear.com==- 是, 首相  第1季第5集
本字幕仅供学习交流，严禁用于商业用途
-=破烂熊字幕组=- 翻译&校对&时间轴: tpring
休戚相关
你好啊 亲爱的 内阁会议顺利吗?
Hello, darling. Good Cabinet meeting?
内阁会议顺利吗 亲爱的?
Hmm. Good Cabinet meeting, darling?
我要三份威士忌      这么惨 怎么啦?
I want a triple Scotch! As bad as that? Why?
经济危机比预期严重得多 内阁各部门都得削减开支
The crisis is worse than we thought. the Cabinet must make cuts.
伯纳 来杯威士忌吗?      好的 请给大杯行吗?
Bernard, would you like a Scotch? Yes, a large one, please.
也来三份
Another triple
伯纳 汉弗莱该预料到这个 警告我
Humphrey should have seen this coming.
我认为他不懂经济 首相 他念的古典文学
I don't think he understands Economics. He did read Classics.
弗兰克爵士呢? 他是财政部首脑
Sir Frank is head of the Treasury.
恐怕他更不可能懂经济 他是个经济学家
greater disadvantage in understanding Economics. He's an economist.
经济危机了 内阁大臣料不到要削减经费吗?
Can't they see there's got to be cuts?
都料到在别的部门 轮不到他们自己
In other departments, not in their own!
今天早晨你下限制令啦?
So you ordered a clampdown?
我没权力下令 我不过是个首相      可你负全责啊
I can't do that. I'm only the Prime Minister. But you're in charge.
不 领导人只能听别人意见 服从多数 这是民主
A leader can only lead by consent, consensus. That's democracy.
你不负责 那到底谁负责?      没人负责
So who IS in charge? Nobody, really.
这样好吗?      肯定好 这就是民主的目的
Is that good? It must be. That's what democracy is about.
麻烦的是 下午还有个议员代表团来找我
And I've got a deputation of MPs coming
商量我答应给他们加薪的事
to see me about a pay rise I promised them.
你要怎么说?      我会说我非常同情 其实我没有
What will you say? That I deeply sympathise. I don't.
加薪是他们应得的 其实不是
That they fully deserve it. Not true.
只要危机过去我打算当作头等大事来抓 其实我没这打算
my first priority as soon as the crisis is over. I shan't.
如果他们投票给自己大幅加薪 然后宣布没钱给别人加
If they vote themselves a whacking great pay rise,
也不会给议会增光添彩 确实不会
it doesn't do very much for the dignity of Parliament. It doesn't.
他们真的报酬过低吗?      报酬过低?后座议员?亲爱的
Are they underpaid? Underpaid?! Backbench MPs? Darling...
议员是个名利双收的顶级肥差
Being an MP is a vast, subsidised ego trip.
没有资质考核 没有固定时数 没有评价标准
You need no qualifications, no compulsory hours of work, no performance standards.
用舒适的房间和美食养活一帮自大狂和无事忙
A warm room and meals for a bunch of windbags and busybodies
他们突然发现人们把他们当回事了
who suddenly find people taking them seriously
因为名字后面加了"议员"两个字
because they've got ''MP'' after their names!
他们怎么会报酬过低? 每个位置有200人申请呢
there's about 200 applicants for every vacancy?
就算要交钱上任 每个位置还能卖20次
You could fill every seat 20 times if they paid to do the job!
你5年前还是后座议员呢
You were a backbench MP only 5 years ago.
我是特例
I was the exception.
我是精华 我升到顶峰了
I was the cream. I rose to the top.
你觉得这说法能压住他们吗?      谁知道
Do you think you'll shut them up? Who knows?
可公众绝不会答应议员涨工资 而护士和教师做削减
The public will never stand when cut back on nurses and teachers.
护士和教师 这问题可严重多了
Oh, that's a much more serious problem.
不 亲爱的 差远了 护士和教师
No, darling, much LESS serious. They
不到下次大选不能投票反对我
can't vote against me till the next election.
后座议员今晚10点就能投我的反对票
Backbenchers can do it at 10 o'clock tonight.
汉弗莱 我刚跟议员们开了个很激烈的会
Humphrey, I've just had a very stormy meeting with my backbenchers!
真遗憾      要是给我点预警 我能先把他们缓和下来
I'm so sorry. If I had warning, I'd have softened them up.
可内阁会议前夜文件才送到      是吗 首相 真令人遗憾
Papers only arrived the night before Cabinet! Most regrettable.
怪你 汉弗莱 你是内阁秘书 你得负责让文件早点送来
You must insist that we get papers circulated earlier.
唉 恐怕文件还没撰写 送来就有很大困难
grave problems in circulating papers before they are written.
怎么突然闹危机 财政部料到了吧?
Why the sudden crisis?
首相 我不是财政部常任秘书 您得问弗兰克爵士
Prime Minister, you must ask Sir Frank.
弗兰克爵士会怎么说?
What would Sir Frank say?
轮不到鄙人这样卑微的凡人
It is not for a humble mortal such as I
对伟人们复杂深远的谋略妄加揣测
to speculate on the complex and deliberations of the mighty,
但总的来说 弗兰克爵士大概认为
but, in general, I think Sir Frank believes that
如果财政部觉得有必要采取某一行动
if the Treasury knows something must be done,
内阁不该有太多时间来考虑它
the Cabinet shouldn't have time to think about it..
太不像话了
Outrageous!
的确 此所谓财政部政策      如果内阁有问题呢?
It's known as Treasury policy. Suppose the Cabinet has questions?
我想他认为 就算财政部难得地理解了问题
on the rare occasions when the Treasury understands the questions,
内阁也不会理解答复
the Cabinet doesn't understand the answers.
你支持这个看法吗?      我吗 首相
Do you subscribe to that view? I, Prime Minister,
我只想尽力达成首相和内阁的愿望
I merely try to carry out your wishes.
我希望今后一切文件在内阁会议前48小时送到
all Cabinet papers be circulated at least 48 hours in advance.
告诉弗兰克爵士好吗?     好 当然
Would you tell Sir Frank? Yes, of course.
我这就去请求他接见 谢谢 首相
I shall seek an audience with him at once. Thank you.
弗兰克以为他是谁? 至少小汉还有自知之明
Who does Frank think he is? At least Old Humpy knows his place.
他真忠诚 居然告诉我真相 他们不是总抱成一团的吗
It was very loyal of him to tell me the truth.
我想他很担心您提出的 让弗兰克爵士取代他
He's rather anxious because of your threat to make Sir Frank
做公务员首脑的事
head of the home Civil Service.
对啊 不知道我是把这件事解决掉呢
Of course. I wonder if I should do something about that.
还是让他俩都提心吊胆的比较有利
Or if to keeping them both in suspense.
首相 您会得到一个紧张的内阁秘书 您乐意吗?
You gain an anxious Cabinet Secretary. Is that what you want?
他不仅是不满意削减的事 弗兰克
He wasn't just unhappy about the cuts, Frank.
他最不满意的是你的文件那么晚才送到
He was unhappy about your papers arriving at such short notice.
你跟他解释了这是因为美国突然调整利率吧
I hope you explained it was because of America's policy change.
亲爱的弗兰克 我对你大加维护
My dear Frank, I defended you gallantly,
让首相对真正原因没有一点怀疑
leaving the Prime Minister in no doubt as to the real cause.
那就好 多谢
Oh, good. Thanks.
我需要他的支持      为什么?
I'll need his goodwill. Why?
显然 因为经济危机 我们得实施些薪酬限制政策
We shall obviously have to bring in some form of pay restraint.
问题是 如果拒绝给议员加薪
The problem is, the MPs are being denied their pay rise
正赶上我们提出公务员加薪计划...
just as we bring forward the proposed Civil Service pay rise.
这就尴尬了      对
Ah. That's an awkward one. Yes.
当然 人并不在乎个人利益      当然不
One isn't interested for oneself... Of course not.
但人总要为下级同僚们着想      真讽刺 对吧 弗兰克?
But one does owe it to one's junior colleagues. Ironic, isn't it
为他们办事 我们也不得不加薪 我们明明不在乎的
Trying to help them involves raising our own salaries
还要被人骂作是营私自肥
And then we get accused of feathering our own nests!
这也是我们不得不担的罪名
That's just another cross we have to bear.
对 嫉妒 纯粹是嫉妒
Yes. Envy, pure envy.
你得趁薪酬限制启动前 赶紧提出加薪计划
You'd better get that proposal in before the pay restraint begins.
就在下周四内阁会议前夜
The night before next Thursday's Cabinet.
我们不能给大臣们两天时间
We can't let Ministers spend two days talking about it.
跟政治顾问和议员讨论 他们会提出各种愚蠢的反对意见
They'll come up with stupid objections!
一直把它压到薪酬限制启动
And try to delay it until the pay restraint.
你真的觉得可以跳过两周内阁议程?
Do you think it's all right to bounce the Cabinet running?
没别的办法      我在想 汉弗莱
No alternative. I-I-I was thinking, Humphrey.
也许计划由我们两个共同提出比较稳妥
Perhaps it would be better if the proposal came from both of us.
我们两个?      我们毕竟是公务员的联合领导嘛
Both of us? Well, we are joint heads of the Civil Service.
照我理解不是 弗兰克
Not as I understand it, Frank.
我认为 实际上是的      我认为实际上不是
Oh, I think so, effectively. I think not, effectively.
我管财政方面 你管体制
I look after the financial side and you the establishment side.
可弗兰克 恕我直言 内阁秘书理应被赋予公务员领导权
the Cabinet Secretary is the de jure head of the Civil Service.
恕我直言 汉弗莱 内阁秘书和财政部常任秘书
the Cabinet Secretary and the Permanent Secretary to the Treasury
实务上是在共同领导公务员
are de facto joint heads of the Civil Service.
就算是 弗兰克 我们不能一起提
Be that as it may, Frank, we can't put up the proposal together.
我得保持冷漠和公正
I must remain aloof and judicial.
得由你来发动 经过缜密思考 我再站到你这边来
After weighty consideration, I will come down on your side.
好吧 还有件事
All right. One other point...
显然 我们不能让内阁来裁定
We don't want Cabinet to adjudicate on this.
对 得成立中立委员会审查      谁来做主席?
They must refer it to an impartial committee. Who should chair it?
韦尔斯教授如何?      那个昏聩的老傻瓜?
What about Professor Welsh? That silly old buffer?!
那个昏聩的老傻瓜      为什么?
That silly old buffer. Why?
他要我提名他做大学补助委员会主席
He's asked to be the chairman of the University Grants Committee.
他极其想要那职位 他会理解我们的要求
desperate for the job, so he'll understand what's required of him.
真是明智之选
What an excellent choice.
汉弗莱 我太震惊了
Humphrey, I'm astonished.
财政部刚因为经济危机砍掉了一半开支计划
The Treasury has just cancelled half our spending plans
现在他们居然有胆提出公务员加薪计划
and now they put forward a plan for a Civil Service pay rise!
你还想让它跳过内阁会议
And you're bouncing it through Cabinet!
我说了要所有文件提前48小时送到
I wanted all papers circulated 48 hours in advance.
你觉得我纯粹是白痴吗?
Do you think I'm a complete idiot?
首相 我没权利为弗兰克爵士辩护
It is not for me to speak for Sir Frank.
我要你为自己辩护 你是内阁秘书 也是公务员的领导
Speak for yourself. You're head of the Civil Service.
我是吗? 真让人欣慰      眼下是
Am I indeed? How gratifying! For the moment.
可首相 作为内阁秘书 我也急于削减公共开支
As Cabinet Secretary, I am most eager to reduce public spending,
但作为公务员领导 我得对眼前的行政危机负责
as head of the Service I'm responsible for dangers administratively
如果加薪不能尽快通过的话
if a pay rise does not come through very soon.
我真的很难办 您看 我顶着两个头衔
It's so difficult for me. I'm wearing two hats.
这倒是 你确实很难应付吧?
Yes, isn't that rather awkward for you?
不会 如果有两副头脑的话
Not if one is in two minds.
或者有两副面孔
Or has two faces.
要不要我给你解除一个?
Perhaps I should relieve you of one of them?
不用不用 我非常乐意有两个      面孔?
Oh, no, no, no. I'm perfectly happy with both. Faces?
头衔
Hats!
您看 首相 问题在于士气低下会导致罢工
the problem is that low morale will lead to the danger of a strike.
想想社会服务业电脑员罢工的后果吧
Think of the effect of that on the social services.
再说 我们的招募已经有困难了
And we are already experiencing difficulties in recruitment.
每个职位有10个人申请吧?      对 可申请者素质非常低下
10 applicants for every vacancy? very low quality.
很少人拿一等学位 大多数都只有二等乙级
With very few First Class degrees. Most have Lower Seconds.
我拿的三等
I got a Third.
这对首相足够了 汉弗莱爵士是说公务员
That's all right for PM. Sir Humphrey means civil servants.
重点是 我想批也批不了 后座议员的威胁还没解除呢
The point is There's already a backbench revolt looming.
议员们绝不会同意给公务员加薪 内阁也会反对
MPs will never agree to a pay rise for civil servants.
我能否建议只请内阁过目一下计划?
ask the Cabinet merely to agree to look at the application?
然后把它交给独立小组 详察细节
Then we'll put the matter before an independent group of assessors.
谁来主持评审?      我有个完美的人选
Who would lead these assessors? There's a very good man
韦尔斯教授 非常可靠 非常明智 非常慎重
Professor Welsh. Very sound, very sensible, very careful.
我听说他是个昏聩的老傻瓜
I heard he was a silly old buffer.
真难以想象什么人会说出这种话
I can't imagine who could possibly say such a thing!
由于公务员中最高的两个职位负担最重
Since the most senior grades of the service bear the heat
他们加薪的幅度也最大
they should receive the greatest increase.
我觉得很公平
Seems very fair to me.
这就是预期幅度      好
So this would be the scale. Right.
对了 我可没看过      当然没有 太不合适了
I haven't seen this, by the way. Of course not. Most improper.
对 好吧 副秘书长加了不少啊
they're very significant increases for Under Secretaries,
常务副秘书长也是
Deputy Secretaries and, um,
而我们中最...
those of us who, um...
正是
Exactly.
大约43%
About 43%.
哎呀      不比我们应得的多
Alas. But no more than we've earned.
这份文件不是用来提交的吧
I take it this paper is not for submission.
亲爱的汉弗莱 这才是要提交的文件
My dear Humphrey, those are the submission papers.
哦 对了
Oh, yes.
这才到附录K      抱歉 后面还有6份
It only goes up to Appendix K. Sorry. Six more to follow.
哦 那他们就没有读完的危险了
Oh! No danger of their wading through all those.
给内阁的一页摘要呢?
Where's the one-page summary for the Cabinet?
傻瓜版?
The Janet and John bit?
在这里
Here it is.
跟上次差不多 与工业职位对照表
It's more or less the same as last time.
和什么人的报酬对照?      当然是英国石油和IBM的董事
On whose salary are the comparisons based? The directors of BP
不会被指为过高和非典型吧?
You don't think that might be challenged as untypical?
不会 我们当然不提名字 只叫他们"典型工业公司"
we don't mention them by name. Just ''typical industrial firms''.
然后我们提出我们的加薪例子 从最低阶开始
Then we take our own examples of increases from the lowest point
照老规矩      主要个体例子附在后面
As before. Principal examples are there at the end.
通信员每周加3.5磅 登记文书每周4.2磅
?.50 a week for a messenger. ?.20 for a registry clerk.
科技官员8.2镑 聊胜于无
?.20 for a scientific officer. Hardly anything.
那我们每年要加26000镑?
So it would be ?6,000 a year extra for us?
差不多吧
More or less.
希望你没提这个吧?      亲爱的汉弗莱
You haven't mentioned that, I hope. My dear Humphrey...
弗兰克 你不觉得这东西有被人仔细审查的危险吧?
you don't think there's a danger that someone go into detail?
不是说它有什么错      谁会审查? 大臣只听我们的简报
Not that there's anything wrong with it. But who?
我们都是忠诚的公务员 都想加薪
We're all loyal members of the service.
对 我等到内阁会议当天午餐前再排到议事日程里去
Yes. I'll get it in last item before lunch on the Cabinet's agenda.
整个议程里 他们顶多花5分钟      四平八稳
They won't spend more than 5 minutes on it. Plain sailing.
只有韦尔斯教授会来严格审查
Apart from the rigorous scrutiny of Professor Welsh.
首相 您首席政治顾问的电话
Your Chief Political Advisor is on the phone.
谢谢 接过来 多萝西?
Thank you. Put her through. ..Dorothy?
首相 我在写关于公务员加薪计划的报告
I'm doing a paper on this Civil Service pay claim,
但我现在就得给您答复
but I can give an immediate response.
好的 什么答复?      没有答复 是一系列问题
Yes, please. What's your answer? It's a series of questions.
问我?      问汉弗莱爵士
For me? For Sir Humphrey.
这份计划自私又不合时宜 很多问题有待回答
The claim is self-serving and inappropriate
好 问吧      好 这事您应该严格保密 不然捉不住他
Right. Fire away. You should treat this as highly confidential.
首先 您应该询问减除额标准...
First of all, you should ask what deduction...
好...
Yes...
太棒了
Triffic!
乔治 这是给你的 我可以进去吧 伯纳?
All right for me to go in, Bernard?
可以 汉弗莱爵士 我能先说件事吗?
Uh, yes. Sir Humphrey, can I just mention one thing?
什么 伯纳?
Yes, Bernard?
起了些变化      哪方面?
There has been movement. On what subject?
公务员希望不起变化的那方面
On a subject we hoped for no movement.
公务员的总体愿望是 一切方面都不起变化
The Civil Service generally hopes there will be no movement on any subject!
对 我是说在某些通常一贯由公务员
it's in relation to a subject that is wholly and exclusively
全权掌控的方面 展开了些进展
within the control of the Service that developments have developed.
你在打谜语 伯纳      谢谢
You're speaking in riddles! Oh, thank you.
这不是夸你 伯纳 拜托说清楚点
That was NOT a compliment, Bernard! Make yourself clear, please.
很抱歉 汉弗莱爵士 我不能透露
I'm sorry, Sir Humphrey, my lips are sealed.
我指的是我有责任记录的一次机密谈话
minutes that I was to make of a confidential conversation
发生在首相和一名顾问之间
between the Prime Minister and an advisor.
哪个顾问?      抱歉 我无权透露那位女士的名字
Which advisor? I cannot divulge her name.
谢谢 伯纳 这些机密建议是关于经济危机的?
And this confidential advice was to do with the financial crisis?
不 汉弗莱爵士 更严重      是他的蠢核武战略?
No, much more important. Not his silly nuclear strategy?
还要严重得多      不是公务员加薪吧?
Much more important. You don't mean the Civil Service pay claim?!
明白了 你有什么建议 伯纳?
I see. What do you advise, Bernard?
我建议您仔细掂量您的位置 采取更加灵活的姿态
consider your position carefully, adopting a more flexible posture,
耳朵贴地 注意动静 腿脚放灵 盯紧背后
keeping ear to the ground, covering your retreat watch your rear.
谢谢 伯纳 你帮了大忙了
Thank you, Bernard. You've been a great help.
实际上 汉弗莱爵士 我什么都没告诉您
Actually, I haven't told you anything.
那当然 伯纳 太不合适了      首相 汉弗莱爵士来了
That's most improper. Prime Minister, Sir Humphrey's here.
灵活
Flexible.
啊 汉弗莱 进来      谢谢 首相
Ah, Humphrey! Come in. Thank you, Prime Minister.
说说你对这个有何看法
Tell me what you think of this.
你觉得怎样?
What do you make of it?
这么多内容 一时很难判断      就读那一页摘要
rather large for instant judgement. read the one-page summary.
哦 好的      怎样?
Ah. Oh, good. Well?
怎样?
Well?
首相 您可让我进退两难了
Prime Minister, you place me in a very difficult position.
是吗 汉弗莱? 我知道你得忠于同僚们
Do I, Humphrey? You have to have loyalty to your colleagues
但更重要的是 要忠于内阁及其政策
but also to Cabinet policies.
我同意      你同意?
I agree. You agree?
对      你同意我?
Yes. With me?
我同意您      我...我不...你同意什么?
I agree with you. I...ah... I don't... Who do you agree with?
同意您      不是同意弗兰克爵士?
With you. Not with Sir Frank?
不      你不跟我争辩?
No. You're not arguing with me?
不
No.
也许我说得还不够清楚
Perhaps I haven't made myself quite clear.
我同意您
I agree with you!
那你对这个加薪计划有何看法?
Well, what do you make of that pay claim?
这个 本身来说不算过分
Well, it's not excessive in itself,
但值此国家危机之际 它既不明智也不符合国家利益
but at a national stringency neither wise nor in national interest.
我不愿意批评我的同僚 可是
I don't like to criticise my colleague, but...
我认为弗兰克爵士 尽管本意无疑是好的
though no doubt acting from the best of motives,
应该把国家利益置于公务员的狭隘利益之上
should have placed the good of the nation before civil servants.
您看 这份计划有些严重问题
You see, this claim raises serious questions.
真有意思 我自己也记了几个问题
That's interesting. I've made a note of some questions, too.
好问题 哪里来的?
Good questions. Where did they come from?
我想到的      对
Oh, occurred to me. Yes.
确实是...非常好的问题
They're...VERY good questions.
对 我也这么觉得 我们拿它怎么办?
Yes, that's what I thought. What should we do?
我们提出来      向谁提?
We should ask them. Ask who?
向弗兰克爵士 您应该请他过来讨论
Sir Frank. You ought to invite him here to discuss them.
他很可能知道答案 他应该知道
He may well know the answers. Indeed, he should know them.
话说回来 这是他的职责
That's his job, after all.
对 谢谢 汉弗莱 安排一下好吗 伯纳?
Yes. Thank you. Arrange that, Bernard.
我得说 我非常感激你的中立 汉弗莱
I must say I appreciate your impartiality.
如果这个通过 你的赚头也不小
You'd gain quite a lot yourself if it were to go through.
大概是吧 首相 不过
Well, I suppose so, Prime Minister,
坦白说 我认为这份工作的回报 就是知道
but I see the rewards of this job as the knowledge...
我们得以造福国家 而非造福我们自己 您说呢 首相?
..that we've been of service to the nation, not to ourselves.
我同意 谢谢 汉弗莱      谢谢您 首相
I agree. Thank you, Humphrey. Thank you, Prime Minister.
汉弗莱真是公正 对吧?      对 首相
Humphrey's very fair-minded, isn't he? Oh, yes, Prime Minister.
如果真有利益冲突 公务员究竟站哪边?
If there were a conflict which side are the Service really on?
赢的那边 首相
The winning side, Prime Minister.
谢谢 比利 我真的很痛心没能支持弗兰克
It was very painful for me not to be able to support Frank's case.
非常令人沮丧      可他肯定会输
Deeply distressing. But he was going to lose.
韦莱那个女人给首相列了一堆问题
And that Wainwright female had suggested
建议不让我们处理自己的加薪计划
that they stop us handling our own pay claims
成立一个议会特选委员会来决定
and let a Select Committee decide on them!
太过分了 接下来政客会以失职为理由
Next thing you'd have is politicians removing civil servants
开除公务员了 这是导火索      就是
on the grounds of incompetence! The thin end of the wedge.
阿诺德 我需要你帮助 显然 弗兰克的计划不合适
Arnold, I need your help. Clearly, Frank's claim is discredited,
但我必须促成加薪 才能巩固我的位置
but I need to get us the pay rise to consolidate my position.
换你会怎么办 你做内阁秘书的时候怎么办的?
What did you do?
你说弗兰克用了通用方案 跟工业对比?      没错
You say Frank used the normal formula? That's right.
你需要加43%      差不多吧
And you need 43%. Hm. Thereabouts.
既然所有相关人员实际上都在伦敦工作
Well, since virtually all the relevant staff work in London,
首先提高伦敦津贴 津贴属于费用
start with a big increase in the London allowance. Allowances count as expenses.
不算薪水 不计入百分比      伦敦津贴
They don't show in the percentage calculation. London allowance.
然后施行学位特别津贴 给一等和二等甲级文凭的人
introduce a graduate allowance for Firsts and Upper Seconds.
帮助招募新人      牛津没有二等甲级
To aid recruitment. Oxford doesn't give Upper Seconds.
牛津的二等至少能算二等甲级
A second at Oxford counts as an Upper Second, at least.
然后把优异功绩奖加倍 这个奖还在吧?
Then you double the Outstanding Merit awards.
对 人人都有
Oh, yes. Everyone.
这也不算加薪 多少了?
They don't count as rises either. Getting there?
只剩18%要加了      从上次开始计算?
That gets us down to only about 18%. Since last time?
别从上次算 从1973年 加薪百分比的顶峰
Then don't calculate from last time. Calculate from 1973
也别算到今年 算到两年后 加薪阶段末期
And don't just take it to this year. Take it up to two years' time
再考虑通货膨胀 应该够了
Correcting for inflation, that should do it.
好极了 现在增幅显得很公正了 可还有个问题
Excellent. The percentage increases will sound all right now
公务员薪金支出总额仍然太高
The overall Civil Service pay bill will still be too high.
简单 缩减公务员规模      什么?
Easy. Reduce the size of the Civil Service. What?!
如果总规模比上次小 个人合理加薪的总额就相应小了
If the service were smaller, a comfortable rise looks smaller.
对 可是缩减公务员规模?
Real reductions in the size of the service?!
这会是我们文明的终结
It would be the end of civilisation as we know it!
不 亲爱的汉弗莱 你只须不再叫他们公务员
No, All you do is stop calling them civil servants.
比如说博物馆吧
Take the museums, for instance.
把它们改成独立基金 职员就不算公务员了
turn them into trusts, the staff stop being called civil servants.
还是一样的人 做一样的动作 拿政府拨款
same people doing the same job and still paid by government grants,
但拨款这东西不计入薪酬 除非有人仔细审查
but as it's a grant it doesn't count in the pay statistics.
不然看上去就像削减
it will look like a cutback.
能突然设立这么多基金吗?
Can we set up so many trusts in time?
不需要 只要计划在未来两年内就行
You won't have to. It only has to be planned.
如果最后没达成 没人会要你负责
If it doesn't happen, it won't be your fault.
同时 你应该可以把增幅控制在6%了
you should be able to get the rise to work out at 6% overall.
谢谢 阿诺德 多亏你了      我一向乐意帮忙
Thank you, Arnold. That's a great help. Always happy to oblige.
尤其是生日和授勋临近的时候
Especially with the birthday honours coming up.
要我也跟弗兰克说说吗?
Should I talk to Frank about this, too?
不不 阿诺德 交给我吧 弗兰克问题够多了
Leave it to me. Frank's got a lot of problems coming up.
真的?他可没提到      大概因为他还不知道吧
He hasn't mentioned them. Because he doesn't know about them yet.
而且公务员薪酬大大落后于同等工业职务
Service pay has fallen behind comparable jobs in industry.
什么同等职务?
What comparable jobs?
这个比较方案很复杂 不过多年来都被普遍接受
it's quite complex but it has been accepted for some time.
我知道常任秘书年薪超过45000镑
I understand that a Permanent Secretary earns over ?5,000 a year.
内阁秘书和财政部常任秘书超过51000镑
Permanent Secretary to the Treasury earn in excess of ?1,000.
也许是这样
Um...maybe you're right.
你不知道你挣多少吗 弗兰克? 还是突然忘了?
Don't you know how much you earn or has it slipped your memory?
对 可如果跟工业报酬比...
Yes, but if that's what industry is paying...
你觉得呢 汉弗莱?      这不由我说 首相 我有既得利益
What do you think, Humphrey? It's not for me to say.
弗兰克爵士负责公务员报酬 对吧弗兰克?
Sir Frank is in charge of Civil Service pay.
首相 我能问个问题吗?      好
Prime Minister, may I ask a question? Yes.
弗兰克爵士 你在职位保障方面的减除额是多少?
What deduction do you make for job security?
你说什么?      工业首脑有失业之虞
I beg your pardon? Top people in industry can get sacked.
开除 调走 公司破产 可你的职位雷打不动
They can go bust, but your jobs are guaranteed.
有得有失嘛      什么失?
There are swings and roundabouts. What roundabouts?
工作时间长      工业里就不长吗?
Long hours. Don't those happen in industry?
工业首脑还得做决定
Industrial leaders must stand by decisions.
公务员也是      真的? 不是大臣做决定嘛
So do civil servants. Really? I thought ministers took decisions.
还担责任 是这么安排的吧?      对 大臣是得做决定
And the blame. Yes, ministers do take the decisions.
公务员得决定如何贯彻
Civil servants must decide how to carry it out.
就像秘书起草一封信      对
Like a secretary laying out a letter. Yes.
不 汉弗莱爵士明白我的意思
No! Um... Sir Humphrey knows what I mean.
得由你说 弗兰克 你负责公务员报酬
It's up to you, Frank. You're in charge of Civil Service pay.
那公益服务成份呢?
What about the service element?
公益服务成份? 什么意思?
Service element? What do you mean?
这份工作有很强的公益性      可不是
The job has a strong element of service. Absolutely.
报酬是巴思爵士 二等勋爵士 骑士勋位 弗兰克爵士
Rewarded by CBs and KCMGs and knighthoods...Sir Frank.
从某种意义上说
To an extent.
首相 也许我们更应该把公务员比作慈善机构董事
shouldn't compare civil servants with directors of charities
而不是工业董事 他们平均年薪17000镑 不是45000
rather than industries. They get ?7,000 a year on average
这个提议有意思      不 我认为...那我们永远招不到人了
That's an interesting proposal. We'd never recruit.
士气会直线下降 汉弗莱爵士肯定同意
Morale would plummet. I'm sure Sir Humphrey would agree.
汉弗莱?      我的意见是
Humphrey? Well, it's my opinion that...
弗兰克爵士负责公务员报酬
..Sir Frank is in charge of Civil Service pay.
我认为首相完全有权得到答复 弗兰克
I do think the Prime Minister is entitled to an answer, Frank.
还有物价指数化退休金问题      对 这个早就有共识了
Then there are indexed pensions. those were agreed a long time ago.
价值非常大 对吧      价值 对 可并不过分
They're of considerable value. Of value, yes, but modest.
这份估价说 买断一位常任秘书的退休金要65万镑
it would cost ?50,000 to buy back a Permanent Secretary's pension.
荒谬      你估计呢?
Absurd. How do you value it?
大约10万磅      那好 我们做个交易 弗兰克
Er, about ?00,000. In that case, I'll make you a deal, Frank.
由政府买断你的退休金 别人乐意出售也行
The government will buy back your pension
就照你的估价 我们给你10万磅现金 好吗?
at your own valuation. 100,000 in cash for your pension rights?
我说的是...就是随口一说 不可能...
I was talking out of my...off the top of my head.
我自己也没算过
I haven't calculated it myself.
65万这个数字来自保险和退休金精算协会
The figure of ?50,000 comes from the Society of Insurance
对 可当初达成的共识肯定不是这样
Yes, but when it was agreed I'm sure it was nothing like that.
这个主意怎样? 物价指数化退休金和勋位平行
An indexed pension could be an alternative to honours.
每位公务员自行选择 要勋位还是钱
Every civil servant could choose honours or cash.
无稽之谈     为什么?
That's preposterous! Why?
对啊 为什么?      这个 它 它...
Yes, why? Well, it, it, it, it, it...
它会让我们...让他们很为难的 有些已经有勋位了
It would put us put THEM in an impossible position.
简单 他们可以选择放弃勋位还是放弃钱
They could choose whether to renounce their honour or pension
你觉得呢 汉弗莱爵士? 或者阿普比先生?
What do you think, Sir Humphrey? Or will you be Mr Appleby?
我肯定弗兰克爵士已经彻底考虑过了
I'm sure that Sir Frank has gone into this very thoroughly.
还不够彻底 你自己也会赚到不少 对吧?
Not thoroughly enough. You'd stand to gain quite a lot personally.
首相 这不列入考虑
Prime Minister, that is not a consideration.
你乐意你个人被剔除出这次加薪?
You'd be happy to be personally excluded from this rise?
我知道内阁秘书肯定乐意 是吧汉弗莱?
I know the Cabinet Secretary would be.
当然 问题是...本质上 这种先例...
Well, of course, the question is... not as a precedent...
通盘考虑整个公务员系统...
..thinking of the service as a whole...
从 从长远角度来说 原则上要求...
from the long-term point of view... as a matter of principle...
说呀      当然
Go on. Well, of course...
如果...
..IF...
如果...政府真的相信
..if...the government did believe
高阶人员应该比下属拿得少
that senior people should be paid less than their subordinates,
如果这一原则延伸到内阁大臣和新晋大臣
and if the principle were extended to Cabinet ministers
总之 弗兰克 多谢你过来
Anyway, Frank, thank you very much for coming in.
谢谢您 首相
Thank you, Prime Minister.
你觉得怎样 有点苛刻吧?      不 非常合适而有见地的问题
A bit hard? No. Most proper and penetrating questions.
现在怎么办?      我想跟您私下说一句
What happens now? I'd like a word in private.
我正要走      好 多萝西
I was just going. Good.
真是太感谢你了      亲爱(珍贵)的女士
Thank you very much indeed. Dear lady.
可比不上内阁秘书贵 汉弗莱
Not as dear as a Cabinet Secretary, Humphrey.
首相 我真的很难着手 我痛恨对同僚不忠诚
One does so hate to be disloyal to one's colleagues.
显然你没当过内阁大臣
Clearly you've never been a Cabinet minister!
我一直都觉得 在这种紧张时期 财政部的要求太过分了
I'd felt all along, at a time of stringency, that the Treasury claim was too high.
不符合国家利益 对公务员当然非常好
Not in the nation's interests. Very nice for us,
但一位高度忠诚的内阁秘书很难苟同
but not something the Cabinet Secretary could recommend.
这就是为什么我们不让财政部常任秘书统领公务员
It's why we don't let the Treasury be head of the Civil Service.
所以我擅自拟定了一份低调得多的计划
So I've drawing up a much more modest submission
未来两年内增加11% 高阶人员仅高于平均数
only 11% over two years with the top grades rising the average
其间公务员薪酬支出总额每年只增加6%
and the overall Civil Service pay bill going up by only 6%
这看上去合理多了
This looks much more reasonable.
对 当然 低阶人员加薪还得经过正常程序
Yes. The lower grades will have to go through the normal procedures,
但我建议高阶人员方面应该立即秘密推行
but the First Division should be processed with secrecy.
秘密 为什么?      如果发起广泛讨论
Secrecy? Why? If there were widespread discussion,
也许会适得其反 我们有些人也许要提出高得多的计划
Some of our people might want to put in a much bigger claim.
造成既成事实比较好
Much better to present a fait accompli.
我建议能否避免...让顾问过目?
And may I advise against letting...advisors see it?
你的同僚真能接受只加6%吗?
Are you sure your colleagues would accept 6%?
如果有您的支持与合作 能的
If I had your support and co-operation, yes.
那还是得议会批准 后座议员痛恨公务员加薪
It's still get through Parliament. They hate Service pay rises.
您提到这点真是太巧了
Oh! How interesting you should say that!
我刚要提个建议 一项重大改革      好
I was just about to make a suggestion, a major reform.
首相 如果把议员的薪酬跟同级公务员挂钩
MPs' salaries were to be linked to a grade in the Civil Service,
他们就不用总投票给自己加薪了
they wouldn't need to vote themselves pay rises all the time.
只要公务员加 他们自动也加
If the Civil Service got one, they'd get one.
如果议员的退休金也物价指数化
And if MPs' pensions were index-linked,
他们对公务员薪酬的敌意会大大缓和的
it would make them much less hostile to Civil Service pay claims.
肯定会 太妙了
It certainly would. Excellent.
谢谢 汉弗莱      首相
Thank you, Humphrey. Prime Minister.
后座议员跟哪级挂钩?
What grade ought backbenchers be?
资深主任吧?      级别太低了吧?
Senior Principals. Isn't that rather low?
后座议员本来就低级
Backbenchers are rather low.
那内阁大臣呢?      副秘书长?
And what grade for Cabinet ministers? Under Secretaries.
首相呢?
And the Prime Minister?
这个嘛 眼下 您的薪水比我还低
Well, at the moment, you earn even less than I do.
何不把您自己与算作常任秘书呢?
Why don't you grade yourself as a Permanent Secretary?
谢谢 汉弗莱      话说回来 我们是合伙关系
Thank you, Humphrey. After all, this is a partnership.
对 真正的合伙关系      是 首相
Yes. A real partnership. Yes, Prime Minister.
破烂熊字幕组 -==www.RagBear.com==- 欢迎加入